Don't cry.
泣いてはダメよ
Hey!
お〜い
Seems that Suo-sama was called by the presbytery.
スオウ様が長老会に呼ばれたそうだ
So finally they started to do something.
やっとなの？
Translator
字 幕 入 力
ssnake
ssnake
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
字 幕 編 集
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
さ  き
さ　　き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
Suo,
スオウ
you have been appointed as the new chief of the mud whale.
おまえを泥クジラの新しい首長に任命する
I accept it respectfully.
…謹んでお受けします
You looks so bad.
顔色が悪いわ
Wash your clothes, it'll disturb our people.
その服も洗いなさい　皆が動揺する
If you can't get the dirt off, we will provide you a new one.
汚れが落ちないようなら　新しいものを支給します
It is not dirt...
…汚れじゃありません
It is Sami's...
これは　サミの…
Oh dear...
まあまあ…
You are still a child.
あなたも　まだ子供だったわね
Suo.
スオウさん
Neli...
ネリ…
Sorry...
ごめん
You can't cry forever, Suo.
いつまでも泣いてはいられないわ　スオウ
Right.
そうだよ
We are also in pain.
我々だってつらいのだ
But there is something you have to do.
だが　やらねばならぬことがある
It's the first and last mission for you, as the chief.
お前には首長としての　「最初で最後」の使命を与える
It was something decided by all the presbyters a few minutes ago.
これは先ほど　長老会全員一致で決定したことだ
We have decided
泥クジラを
to sink the mud whale into the sea of sand.
砂の海に沈めることにしたよ
What do you mean?
どういうことですか？
Then where should we go?
それでは　私たちはどこに…
Where should we live?
どこで暮らせば…
We shall
一緒に…
suicide in the sand, together with the mud whale.
泥クジラと共に砂に召されるのだよ
We hope you can guide us
お前は最後の首長として
to death of proud, as the last chief.
皆を誇りある死へと導いてほしい
This is your first and last mission.
それが　お前の最初で最後の使命だ
Why...
なぜですか…
Why must everybody die!
なぜ皆が死ななくてはならないのですか
Those who attacked us,
我々を襲った者たちは
were from where used to be our mother country.
もともと我々と同じ国の人間だ
Eh...
え…
Our ancestors were exiled to the sea of sand for their guilt.
我々の先祖はある罪で砂の海に流された
The exile is continued till now.
今もその流刑は続いている
And now,
そして今
they have decided to execute us.
彼らは我々を処刑するという決断をした
Those soldiers were intended
あの兵士たちは
to massacre all the people here in mud whale.
泥クジラの民を一人残らず殺すつもりだ
Their purpose is not invasion,
彼らの目的は侵略行為ではない
but execution.
処刑なのだ
There is no way to avoid it.
それを回避するすべはない
Nobody want to see our people be killed miserably
無残に殺される泥クジラの民の姿など
in the mud whale.
誰が見たいものか
For our pride, we shall go to that world ourselves elegantly.
皆の誇りを守るため　その前に穏やかに旅立つのだ
Byakuroku-sama?
ビャクロク様？
Our father... I don't want it.
お父様あ…　いやだよ
I don't want to be killed!
殺されるのはいやだ！
I don't want to be sunk either!
おぼれてしぬのもいやだよぉ…！
He lost himself for a long time.
ご自分をなくしておいでだ
Take Byakuroku-sama to his room.
ビャクロク様を部屋へお連れしろ
The eldest presbyter!
最長老さま
Fine. It will be fine.
大丈夫…　大丈夫です
I will not let you die unreasonably like Sami and Taisha-sama.
サミやタイシャ様のように　理不尽に死なせはしません
Suo!
スオウ！
I don't want anyone to die anymore!
もう誰も死なせたくない！
There must be a way for everybody to survive!
何か皆が生き残る方法があるはずです！
Yes...
そうだ…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
You should ask our father, Fallaina.
お父様　「ファレナ」に聞けばいいの
Fallaina knows everything.
ファレナは　ぜーんぶ知っているよ
Fallaina? The word the girl from that island said...
ファレナ？　島の少女が言っていた…
Doesn't it mean the mud whale?
それは泥クジラのことではないのですか？
Suo! Stop!
スオウ！　よさないか！
You don't need to know it!
おまえは知らなくていい！
Tell me please, the eldest presbyter.
教えてください　最長老さま
What does it mean?
何なのですか
What does it mean exactly by Fallaina...
ファレナとは一体なんのこと…
I should restrain him in such a situation...
こういう場合は彼を拘束する…
I supposed you have told me this.
ということになっていましたが
I should do it, right?
いいんですよね？
Ye... Yes.
え　ええ…
We told you in advance.
前もって話したとおりよ
Strengthen the guard of the underground too, our Captain.
地下の警備も頼むわね　団長さん
How can he say something like that...
あの子があんなことを言うなんて…
He is still young.
彼はまだ幼い
We can't blame him.
しかたのないことだ
We have to change our mood and proceed our task.
気持ちを切り替えて進まなければね
Come on, let's start the preparation.
さあ　準備を始めよう
Neli...
ネリ
What are you writing?
それ　なに書いてんの？
Don... Don't read it!
み…　みないで！
Don't worry, I'm not literate.
大丈夫　アタシ字読めないもん
Also...
てゆうか…
If you don't want other read, don't scribble here.
見られたくないならこんなとこに落書きすんなよな
I was told by Tobikko,
トビっ子に聞いたんだけど
that you succeeded in beating the enemy with your thymia.
サイミア
Only you and Oni have succeeded
あの時あいつらに反撃できたのは
in fighting back against those guys.
オウニとおまえだけだって
How did you make it, destroyer!
デストロイヤーのくせにやるじゃんか！
You are so great!
すげえよ　おまえ！
Stop it.
やめてよ
I haven't done anything.
俺は何もできなかった
That's why Sami died.
だからサミは死んだんだ
I didn't fight back against somebody or beat somebody.
戦うとかやっつけるとかそんな話
And don't tell me that anymore.
もう聞きたくない
That's why you are scribbling your excuses on the wall?
…だから言い訳を壁に書き殴ってるわけ？
Although Samikko died,
サミっ子は死んじゃったけど
you saved the kiddies of Tobikko, didn't you?
トビっ子のチビっ子たちは助かったんだぞ？
Take your credit,
おまえの手柄だ
and be proud!
堂々としろよ
I can't be as easygoing as you.
君みたいにお気楽にはなれないよ
Don't call me you, call me Miss Ginshu!
君じゃない　「ギンシュ姉さん」だ！
It doesn't matter how I call you, right?
呼び方なんてどうでもいいじゃないですか
It matters!
よくない！
It's important how you call me,
人の呼び方ってのはな　大事なんだよ
cuz it shows how you think about me!
その人のことどう思ってるかの表れなんだよ
I will teach you how to use thymia,
アタシがおまえにサイミアの使い方教えてやるよ
so you can fight against those guys when they come again.
またあいつらが来たとき戦えるように
Therefore, call me Miss Ginshu in respect!
だから敬意を込めて「ギンシュ姉さん」なんだよ
Now, call me!
さあ　呼んでみろ！
Miss... Ginshu...
…ギンシュ…　姉さん
That's right!
それでいい！
Do your best, Chakky!
よろしくな　チャッキー！
My name's Chakuro...
…チャクロです
Sucks, it doesn't matter!
んなの　どうだっていいんだよ！
OK, see you again, Chakky!
じゃあ　あとでな　チャッキー！
Chakuro!
チャクロ！
Neli?
ネリ？
You can't climb from here.
そこからじゃ無理だよ
Go around from behind.
後ろから回っておいで
Chakuro.
チャクロさん
It's so beautiful...
綺麗ですね…
But do you know why the world is so beautiful?
この世界が綺麗なのがなぜだか知っていますか？
The souls of the people who have lived here so far,
これまでに生きてきた人々の魂が
are melted into the world.
世界には溶けているんです
For example, you can see it here...
例えば　ここにも…
What is it?
なに？　それ…
This is...
これは…
These people...
あの人たちは…
Sami!
サミ！
Sami, you are alive...
サミ…　生きてたの…
Listen, I wanted...
あのね　あたし…
I wanted to be Chakuro's bride!
チャクロのお嫁さんになりたかった
Sami...
サミ…
Wait, Sami!
待って…　サミ！
I love you too!
俺も好きだった
Even if we Shirushi are short-lived,
たとえ「印」の短い命でも…
we may become bedridden and die very soon,
そのうち体が動かなくなって　死んでしまっても
but it's fine if you can be with me.
君と一緒にいられるならよかった
Even a small wish like this can't be fulfilled...
そんなささやかな願いすら叶えられないなら
Then I'm no longer reluctant to leave this world!
俺は　もうこんな世界に未練はないんだ
Take me there!
そっちへ連れていってよ
That's impossible.
それはダメ
Since Chakuro has a role to play here.
だってチャクロには役割があるんだもん
Wait!
待って
Yes...
そう…
You are the recorder of the truth.
あなたは真実の記録者です
Taisha-sama...
タイシャ様…
The mud whale will be destroyed if you don't do anything.
このままでは泥クジラは滅んでしまいます
Then nobody can know the truth of this island,
誰にもこの島の真実が知らされないまま…
since we will all disappear.
私たちは消えてしまう
You must see everything with your eyes.
あなたは全てを見届けなくてはなりません
It should not be the end of this island...
この島の最後はまだ…
Should not...
まだなのです
Wahh!
うわ！
Oni!
オウニ！
Suo...
スオウ…
Lykos!
リコス！
Neli, have you seen...
ネリ…　今のは…
Hey, haven't you seen Sami and others?
ねえ　君にもサミたちが見えた？
Have you seen Suo and Lykos are suffering?
スオウやリコスの苦しみが…
You are able to feel the hearts of people brilliantly.
あなたは人の心を鮮烈に感じ取ることのできる人
Maybe you think that is useless,
何もできないと思っているかもしれないけれど
but if you don't connect everyone together,
あなたが皆さんを繋げないと
it will be our end.
全ては終わってしまうんです
Chakuro!
チャクロさん
Help me!
助けてください！
I accidentally found that
私　知ってしまったんです
the presbyters is trying to sink the mud whale together with us!
長老会の人たちが
Suo was opposed,
反対したスオウさんは
but he is arrested in the internal area now!
体内エリアに捕らえられてしまいました
Really?
それ　ほんと？
In order to save everybody,
みんなを救うためには
you need to free a person's mind first.
まず　心を解放してあげないといけない人がいます
Please go for her.
行ってあげてください
Lykos?
リコス？
Are you crying?
泣いてるの…？
The ship which I was in,
私がいたあの船は
was intended to attack Fallaina.
もともとファレナを襲うつもりだった
We knew nothing about you.
みんな何も知らなかった
We were told that this island is a hell.
ここは地獄の島だと教えられていたの
But it was us who takes the hell here...
地獄を連れてきたのは
You get to have so many emotions now!
そんなに感情を出せるようになったんだね…
Don't worry.
心配しないで
I have seen your heart twice.
俺は　二度も君の心を見た
I trust you, Lykos.
俺は　リコスを信じてる
By the way, Lykos,
ね　リコス
I need your help.
協力してほしい
We will be sunk into the sea of sand.
このままじゃみんな砂の海に沈んじゃう
What should I do?
何をすればいい…？
But I can hardly believe it.
でも　信じられないんだ
We can't even control the destination of the mud whale.
泥クジラの行き先は誰もコントロールできない
How did the presbytery know
それなのに　長老会が
the method to sink the mud whale.
泥クジラを沈める方法を知ってるなんて
I think I know it.
…私　分かるかもしれない
Is there anywhere
この島のどこかに
that nobody has ever entered in the island?
誰も立ち入ったことのない場所はない？
The internal area! The underground!
「体内エリア」だ！　地下だよ
Though a few parts are used as the prison,
一部は牢獄として使っているけど
there are secret spaces where nobody can enter.
他は誰も入れない秘密の空間があるんだって
Underground...
地下…
Lykos!
リコス！
Ah!
わあ！
It pains...
あたた…
Suo is also arrested underground, I think.
地下には今スオウも捕まってるはず
He also need our help.
彼も助けなきゃ
Pick up the useless arrows carefully!
使えない矢はちゃんと分けておけよ
Yep~
へ〜い
A week will soon be passed.
七日なんて　すぐなんだからな
We have to be prepared for their attacks.
あいつらの襲撃に備えないと
Yes yes.
はいは〜い
Do you really understand?
ほんとに分かってんだか
Oops.
おっと…
Pain!
あだっ！
Masoo, are you OK?
マソオさん　大丈夫？
Ah, yeah.
あ…　ああ
Masoo!
マソオさん！
Nezu! Lo!
ネズ！　ロウ！
It's Chakuro!
チャクロか
We are gathering the weapons for hunting right now.
今狩りの武器を集めてるんだ
You shouldn't do that now!
それどころじゃないんだ！
What? Sink the mud whale?
何だって！　泥クジラが沈む！？
So I need your hands.
だから　力を貸してほしいんだ
Hey wait a moment, it's a mess...
ちょい待てよ　なにがなんだか…
If you are to go oppose the presbytery,
長老会に反対するってことは
you will have to fight against the vigilante group.
自警団とやり合わなくちゃならないってことだろ
The vigilante group?
自警団…？
You really think we can do it with these members?
このメンバーで何とかできる話なのか？
Kicha,
キチャ
Where's... Oni?
オウニ…　は？
Oni!
オウニ！
Cooperate with us!
俺たちに協力して！
What the hell you are!
何だよ　お前！
The mud whale is going to sink into the sea of sand...
このままじゃ泥クジラは砂の海に沈む…
Help us please!
お願いします！
We have been trapped in such a narrow island.
こんな狭い島に閉じ込められて
When we finally found the would outside,
外の世界をやっと見つけたと思ったら
we are trampled by them...
そいつらにメチャクチャにされて…
For me, there's nothing left in such an island.
こんな島に残すものなんかあるのかよ
Enough, I care no more...
もう…　どうでもいい…
An apatheia!
アパトイア
Hey, she's a prisoner?
おい　それは捕虜か？
Yep, we caught her.
そうさ　俺たちが捕まえた
She is a soldier whose emotions have been taken away, and she's alive.
感情を取られた兵士よ　まだ生きてる
Don't touch it!
触るな！
There's no need to treat guys without hearts as a human.
心がない奴を人間扱いしてやる必要なんかない
Whatever I do to it,
俺がこいつをどうしようと…
or abandoning this island like a dishcloth,
この雑巾みたいな島を見捨てようと…
has nothing to do with you!
関係ない！
You are lying.
こんなの　嘘だよね…
Oni, you are not telling your real heart.
オウニは本当の気持ち言ってない
Your fellows died,
仲間が死んじゃって
and your dream and admiration for the world outside has been trashed.
外の世界への夢も憧れも壊されて
I do understand you feel hopeless.
君が希望を持てなくなったのは分かる
But I can see your true heart.
でも…俺には君の本当の心が見えたんだ
You are...
君は…
really willing to protect everybody.
ほんとはみんなを守りたいのに
But you can't find a way, this fact pains you.
その方法が見つからなくて　辛いんだよね？
Chakuro!
チャクロ！
Everybody is trying to decide what should we do.
どいつもこいつも俺たちを決めつけようとする…
Don't make a decision without our own permissions!
俺のことを勝手に決めるな！
Chakuro, you should give up him.
チャクロ　あいつは諦めろ
If you put your time in dealing with that guy,
今あいつともめて時間食ってたら
everybody will be sunk.
みんな沈んじまうんだろ？
Let's go.
行こう…
No, the vigilante group also guards here.
ダメだ　ここも自警団が立ってる
After all, we know there's something underground.
やっぱり地下に何かあんだな
That's enough, let's break it through!
めんどくせえ　突破すんぞ！
It's an emergency, forgive me.
非常時だから許せよ
Masoo you are so strong!
さすがマソオさん！
Don't forget I'm the man who ignored the scouts of the vigilante group!
俺は自警団のスカウトを蹴った男だぞ？
So easy!
甘い甘い
However, I'm a little tired...
とはいえ　ちょっと疲れたな…
Didn't you hear anything?
何か音しなかったか？
Shit, there are more inside.
ゲッ　中にもいたのか？
You guys, help me!
お前ら　頼む！
We are not familiar with the thymia.
俺たち　普段はあんまりサイミア使わないし
That's why I hate the young Shirushi!
これだから最近の若い印は！
What?
あれ？
Chakky! What are you doing?
チャッキー♪　何してんだ？
Gin...
ギン…
What's that Chakky? How did you get that face?
何だよチャッキー　どうした？その顔…
What's up here?
どういうことだ　コレ？
Th... This is...
こっ　これは…
What's up? You guys!
何だ　お前ら！
Miss!
姉さん！
Miss Ginshu!
ギンシュ姉さん！
Dear Miss!
お姉さま！
I want to go inside!
この先へ行きたいんだ
Let me go! Dear Miss Ginshu!
通して！　ギンシュお姉さま！
Hey Ginshu! This guy should...
おい　ギンシュ！　こいつは…
Uwa!
うわ！
Ginshu!
ギンシュ！
We are ordered to prevent people from entering the underground by the presbytery!
誰も地下に入れるなって長老会の命令だろ？
I don't know the reason of their order.
長老会の命令の理由が分かんない
But what I understand well is...
でも　チャッキーが困ってるのは
My Chakky is in trouble!
アタシには　よ〜く分かるんだ！
This is all for my cute Chakky!
これも全て　かわいいチャッキーのためなんだぞ！
Hey, where's Chakky?
って　あれ　チャッキーは？
Chakky!
チャッキー！
Chakky, when did you get so familiar with the vigilante?
チャッキー　おまえいつ自警団と仲良くなったんだ？
I'm not Chakky!
チャッキーじゃない！
Thank you, Ginshu.
ギンシュ　ありがとう
The captain!
団長！
Misfortunes never come alone...
一難去ってまた一難か
That person is strong.
あの人　強い…
Of course!
当然だよ
Only those who are strong in their thymia can enter the vigilant group.
自警団は
And he's the top! The best!
そのトップだから一番できる人なんだよ！
No.1 in the mud whale!
泥クジラで一番！
If he comes...
来るなら…
Wh... What's that... Disappointing.
な…なんだよ　拍子抜けだな
Creepy...
気味悪い…
Well, that's fine. We are facing the internal area.
まあいい　ここから先は体内エリアだ
We can no longer use thymia, so be careful.
サイミアが使えなくなるから気をつけろ
As I thought, it's you.
やっぱり　キミの気配か…
You came to help those kids?
あの子たちの援護に来たってわけ？
That's not somebody like you.
そんな柄じゃないか
You are a bit troublesome.
キミはちょっと厄介かなぁ
I can't let you go~
と〜せんぼ！
However...
…なんて
Come here!
おいでよ
If you want to pass here...
ここを通りたいなら
...let's play!
…遊んだげる♪
Suddenly it becomes quiet.
急に静かになったな
Now we are facing the no-entry area.
この先が進入禁止エリアか
Uwa!
うわ！
Where should Suo be arrested?
スオウはどこに捕まってるんだろう？
Nezu and I will go around the prison and look for Suo.
俺とネズは牢獄を回ってスオウを捜す
Leave it to us!
任せろ
Suo has become our important chief, right?
スオウはもう俺たちの大事な首長様なんだろ？
But how can you get him out...
でも　牢獄からどうやって…
This.
これ
Made by the workshop, used to destroy the lock of prison.
工房作　牢屋の鍵をぶち壊す道具
Hey, what the hell are you guys making!
てめえら　そんなもの作ってたのか！
The presbyters should be in the no-entry area.
長老会は　立ち入り禁止の区域にいるはずだ
We'll go ahead and investigate it. Join us later.
先に行って調べてるから　後で合流しよう
All right!
おう！
Let's go.
行くぞ
Don't you feel heavy?
なんか空気重くないか？
Lykos...
リコス…
What is there over there?
ここには何があるの？
What is the method to sink the mud whale?
泥クジラを沈める方法って何なの？
Hey Chakuro!
なんだよ　チャクロ
You brought us here but you don't even know that?
お前知らずに俺を連れてきたのか？
Sorry.
ごめん
Chakuro,
チャクロ
you have already known it.
あなたはもう知っている
You have touched that... at that time.
あなたがあのとき…触れたことがあるもの
The light...
明かりが…
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
虫の唄
虫の唄
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう